בוקר טוב, Boker tov,
today's דף daf is צדי דלד, tzadi daled, otherwise known as 94.
We start at the beginning of צדי גימל עמוד ב, tzadi gimmel
amud bet, the beginning, the end, sorry about that, of צדי גימל
עמוד ב, tzadi gimmel amud bet, and we are in the middle
of a question about can we apply the principles of believing in
עד אחד eid echad to the issues of יבום. yibum. Now the
גמרא Gemara first framed this as the question of the עד eid
testifies that the husband is dead as in the normal case, but
rather than the woman marrying a strange man, she is going to
marry the brother-in-law. And what would be the reason therefore that this
should change the issue? Well, because the strange man, she's not necessarily
particularly incentivized, or at least not as a regular case,
to cut corners, whereas if it's the brother-in-law, maybe this is somebody
that she's very familiar with, somebody who's been in the family, and
maybe she therefore will be a little bit of cutting corners in
terms of the research that she needs to do, the investigation she
needs to do, because she figures, okay, good, I like the brother-in-law
anyway, maybe I even like him more than my husband.
So that's the question whether we can believe her regarding that. Now
the גמרא Gemara frames it as the question about whether the believability
of an עד אחד eid echad is based solely on the עד
אחד, eid echad, מילתא דעבידא לאיגלויי, milta d'avida l'igluyei, because in the
end, he's testifying to basic facts and about somebody being alive or
dead, and eventually that matter will come to light, so it doesn't
really rely on her investigation and whether she wants it or doesn't
want it is irrelevant, or whether it is really his testimony is
bolstered by the fact that דייקא ומינסבא, diyka u'minsva, that the woman
basically researches it herself. And therefore the question is, when there's a
question about how good of a research she's going to do, can
we still believe an עד אחד? eid echad? So that's very important
because this is the גמרא, Gemara, although before the גמרא Gemara spoke
about the stringencies, חומר שהחמרת לה, chomer shehechmarta lah, etc., this גמרא
Gemara is the one that sort of explicitly lays out this issue
that she will do the research and that that will bolster the
עד אחד. eid echad. Of course תוספות Tosafot is bothered because תוספות
Tosafot assumes that that's what we've always been assuming, and although again
it hasn't been so explicit, you think it's explicit because the ראשונים
Rishonim read it into the earlier סוגיות, sogyos, and therefore how could
the גמרא Gemara suggest it's not based on her research? How could
it suggest it's totally based on the עד אחד? eid echad? So
תוספות Tosafot tries to sort of say, well, it's a little bit
on her research as opposed to a lot on her research and
tries to sort of make that the pervasive reason in order to
smooth over the issues we've been dealing with before. But it's important
to recognize that the גמרא Gemara sets it up as an opposition,
either the עד אחד eid echad on his own or because of
her research. So that's the question when she wants to marry the
brother-in-law. And then the גמרא Gemara now, and the גמרא Gemara though
tries to bring a proof to that because the משנה mishna talked
about a testimony that she was חייב ביבום, chayav b'yibum, and then
that the husband died and the son died and then it was
overwritten. So the גמרא Gemara says overwritten, how could it be overwritten?
Why believe the second report, not the first report? So it says
the only reasonable case would be that the first report was an
עד אחד eid echad and the second report were two witnesses, and
therefore the first report was overwritten, but it shows you that in
principle you would have believed the first report that she could go
ahead and have יבום, yibum, that the son died and then the
husband died. So that was where the גמרא Gemara left it off,
that it sounds like from our משנה mishna that you could believe
an עד אחד eid echad that her husband is dead and that
now she can perform יבום. yibum. So now the גמרא Gemara picks
up on the
following: איכא דאמרי הלא תיבעי לך, ika d'amri halo teebaei lach, four
lines from the bottom. Okay, some say because this was a question
that the students asked רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, that they said that
this isn't the question, whether you can believe the עד eid that
the husband is dead to allow it to remarry, to do יבום.
yibum.
Even a woman is believed to say that her husband is dead
that she can marry, go ahead and do יבום. yibum. דתנן, d'tnan,
we taught in a משנה: mishna: האשה שאמרה מת בעלי תינשא, ha'isha
she'amra met ba'ali tinasei, a woman that says that, oh my gosh,
hold on, that's weird, this whole thing just,
oh for God's sake, I'm sorry, no, this is plugged in, excuse
me a second.
I don't know why, it's got the internet as well. Okay, so,
so it says האשה שאמרה מת בעלי, ha'isha she'amra met ba'ali, woman
that says her husband died,
תינשא, tinasei, she can get married, meaning here's a very important principle
which we haven't yet read in the משנה mishna but it's coming
up, which is that not only can you believe an עד אחד,
eid echad, you can believe the woman's own testimony. She was there
when her husband died, that also works, very important principle, even her
own testimony she can get remarried, or מת בעלי תתייבם, met ba'ali
tisyabem, her husband is dead and that will allow her to do
יבום. yibum. So if you can believe a woman that her husband
is dead to allow her to remarry and to allow her to
do יבום, yibum, then presumably you can certainly believe an עד אחד
eid echad if the same way we're not afraid that her desire
maybe and her interest in her brother-in-law will make her lie, we're
also not afraid that it will make her cut corners and not
do. was sufficient investigation. Now obviously there's a difference as תוספות Tosafos
points out between conscious lying and between not just doing due diligence.
But nevertheless the גמרא Gemara is saying that if you believe her
that her husband is dead to allow her to do יבום, yibum,
you will certainly believe עד אחד ed echad and you won't sort
of say well maybe she's not doing what she needs to do.
So that's not the question. כי איבעיא לך ki ibaya lach what's
the question?
למשרא יבמה לעלמא lemishra yevama le'alma to allow a sister-in-law to marry
another man. Now what would be the scenario you need to believe
עד אחד ed echad to allow the sister-in-law to marry another man?
There could be two obvious cases. One is: everybody knows the husband
is dead, there's a brother-in-law around, we're waiting for יבום yibum or
חליצה, chalitza, and then there's an עד אחד ed echad who reports
that the brother-in-law died, in some foreign country. So can't she now
go ahead and remarry? Okay now this would seem to be a
much less weighty thing. I mean if you can believe עד אחד
ed echad that her husband is dead which is allowing the prohibition
of an אשת איש eshes ish of a married woman which is
an איסור מיתה issur misa and איסור כרת, issur kares, certainly you
should be able to believe עד אחד ed echad that the brother-in-law
is dead that just is to prohibit, allow a much lighter prohibition
of an איסור לאו issur lav that she can't marry another man
until she gets חליצה. chalitza. רבא's Rava going to say that at
the end. But the גמרא's Gemara not so sure that that would
be true and we'll see why. Okay so that's the one scenario.
And the other scenario of allowing her to marry another man and
not worry about יבום yibum is this case about the
report that first the husband died and then her son died as
opposed to the reverse. Right? So if he says the husband died
and then the son died it says you don't need to do
יבום yibum because your son was alive when your husband died. If
it's the reverse then you do need to do יבום. yibum. Okay?
So let's take a look. My computer is acting so weird on
me. Okay so let's take a look.
At the reverse. First and then the husband died.
Right exactly. So that's the question. Can you believe עד אחד ed
echad regarding the fact that she does not require יבום? yibum? So
let's take a look.
So that's כי איבעיא לך אי דאפילו ki ibaya lach i d'afilu
okay etc. למשרא יבמה לעלמא. lemishra yevama le'alma. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama
what? מאי טעמא דעד אחד mai ta'ama d'ed echad why is an
עד אחד ed echad normally believed, again setting up this sort of
alternative two alternative explanations. משום דמלתא דעבידא לאגלויי mishum demilsa d'avida l'igloye
maybe it has nothing to do with her investigation, maybe it has
to do with the fact that it's just a guy's alive or
dead, it's going to get revealed. Right? So therefore לא משקר lo
meshaker the עד ed would
never lie and that is all sufficient to back up the testimony
of the עד אחד. ed echad. So הכא נמי לא משקר hacha
nami lo meshaker so the same would be true about whether the,
for example, the brother-in-law died or whether the husband died before the
son. או דילמא o dilma or maybe, no, like we said before,
טעמא דעד אחד משום דהיא דייקא ומינסבא ta'ama d'ed echad mishum dehie
dayka u'minsva it's not just the testimony of the עד, ed, it's
the testimony of the עד ed bolstered, backed up by her own
research. Okay? And why here might she not do a good job
in terms of the research? והא לא דייקא ומינסבא veha lo dayka
u'minsva she won't do a good job in research, why? דמשנה היא
דסניא ליה demisna hi desanya lei
maybe she hates the brother-in-law. So before we were saying ah so
before we were saying the fact that she might love the brother-in-law,
be interested in him, is not going to compromise her doing her
due diligence. But here we're saying the fact that she hates the
brother-in-law and wants to get out of marrying her would maybe compromise
her due diligence. What's the reason for the difference? So there's a
great תוספות. Tosafos. You look at תוספות Tosafos כי איבעיא לך יבמה
לעלמא ki ibaya lach yevama le'alma תוספות Tosafos says like this: דהתם
איכא למימר טפי לא דייקא שפיר dehasam ika lemimar tfei lo dayka
shapir
there you could say she doesn't do her due diligence משום דסניא
ליה mishum desanya lei maybe she hates the brother-in-law and she's trying
to get out of it. אף על גב דמשום דמרחמא ליה af
al gav demishum demirachma lei even though in the opposite concern that
maybe she was interested in the brother-in-law, לא שבקא מידי למידק lo
shavka midi lemidak she does not תוספות Tosafos כי איבעיא לך ki
ibaya lach דף קט עמוד א. daf kuf tes amud aleph. Sorry
I'm so sorry קט עמוד
א.
kuf
tes amud aleph. So אף על גב דמשום דמרחמא ליה לא שבקא
מידי למידק af al gav demishum demirachma lei lo shavka midi lemidak
even though we said before that because she might be interested in
the brother-in-law she won't stop her from doing her due diligence, משום
דסניא mishum desanya
but if she hates the guy, שבקה טפי shavka tfei she'll more
be negligent in her responsibilities. Why? שגדולה שנאת השונא מאהבת האוהב. shegedola
sinas hasone me'ahavas ha'ohev. Oh
what a true line. Right, hatred is more powerful, right? If she
loves, hates the guy that's a much more powerful force than if
she is interested in the guy. Like you find out, like in
elections or you find out on blogs that the people that are
much more vocal or the people that come out to vote are
the people that are opposed to something and are mad and angry
about something, not the people that support something. Those are the people
that tend to not write as much on the blogs and not
turn out to vote. Okay, so the hatred is much more powerful.
ושכיח טפי דסניא ליה מדרחמא ליה v'shachiach tfei desanya lei midirachma lei
and anyway it's even more common cases of hating the brother-in-law rather
than of loving the brother-in-law כדאמרינן בסוף האשה. kedamrinan besof ha'isha.
That's not as interesting to me. ועוד ve'od now and now he
spells it out: שיותר קשה לה כשתיפול לפניו כששונאתו sheyoser kasha lah
keshetipol lefanav kishesone'aso
besides the fact that the hatred is a more powerful force than
the love, but it's also a much more difficult to live with
the resultant situation if she's going to have to now marry the
guy כשתיפול לפניו כששונאתו keshetipol lefanav kishesone'aso
that's much more difficult ממה שנוח mema shenoach כשתיבא לפניו כששנאתה Ksheteiva
lefanav kshesonatah from what you benefit from the fact that she loves
the guy and she'll be married to him. Why? דכשאוהבת אותו אין
לה כל כך נוח כשתיבא לפניו. Decheshoheves oso ein lah kol kach
noach ksheteiva lefanav. Just because she loves him it's not going to
be so much to her interest that there's going to be a
מצות יבום. mitzvah yibum. Why? כי שמא יחלוץ. Ki shema yachlotz. Number
one, maybe he won't do יבום, yibum, maybe he'll do חליצה, chalitzah,
so she won't even wind up marrying him. ואפילו יכנוס, Ve'afilu yichnos,
and even if he does יבום, yibum, אינה שמחה כל כך, einah
smeichah kol kach, she's not so thrilled, כי הרבה יש לו למצוא
כיוצא בו. ki harbeh yeish lo limtzo kayeozei vo. You know, there
are plenty of fish in the sea, so there's a lot of
other men that maybe she'll be just as happy with. Okay? Well,
also written before the, you know, romanticism and whatever and romantic love
and whatever, but he's a nice guy, there are plenty of nice
guys out there. All right, not such a big loss. Okay, hold
on, כי הרבה יש לו למצוא כיוצא בו, ki harbeh yeish lo
limtzo kayeozei vo,
וטובים ממנו, vetovim mimenu, better people than him. אבל אם שנואה היא,
Aval im snuah hi, but if she hates him, אינה יכולה לינצל
ממנו לינשא לאחר. einah yecholah linatzel mimenu linasei leachair. If she winds
up married him, she can't, she's trapped, right? She has no alternatives.
In one way, worst case scenario, you don't get this guy but
you're free, you can choose, you might marry another guy. In this
case, when she hates him, the worst case scenario is you're trapped
in a marriage with somebody you hate. That's a much worse situation.
Okay, אינה יכולה לינצל ממנו לינשא לאחר, einah yecholah linatzel mimenu linasei
leachair, אם לא יחלוץ, im lo yachlotz, על כרחה צריכה לינשא לשנוא
לה. al karchah tzrichah linasei lesonu lah. So then her choices are
left to be married to somebody that she hates, או תתעגן, o
tiseigein, or maybe never getting יבום yibum or חליצה. chalitzah. So a
very powerful תוספות, Tosafos, A, pertaining to the fact that, yes, you
know, the power of hatred is often stronger than the power of
love, and also the consequences. Not being married to the guy you
love is somehow, you know, is not as consequential. I mean, you
still are free to marry the guy, you know, the next guy
who proposes to you or you're interested in, and is not as
consequential as being trapped in a marriage that's loveless or a marriage
of even somebody that you hate. So anyway, a very powerful תוספות
Tosafos explaining the difference of the גמרא Gemara here. Yes, there was
a question, yes, go ahead.
Didn't we say she could reject the יבם? yavam?
What? Didn't we say she could reject the יבם?
yavam?
Oh, yes,
sometimes.
I mean, that's true,
well no, but no, no, no, he gets to decide. So the
only question is whether the בית דין beis din advises, you know,
the guy or not. But at the end of the day, even
if the בית דין beis din might try to push the guy
in one direction, it still remains the guy's choice. So she doesn't
have a choice?
Not legally. No, no, no, she doesn't legally have a choice. Meaning
that the בית דין beis din might try to push her and
might really try to listen to what she says, but legally speaking,
she doesn't have a choice. Yes.
And that's the first thing I was going to ask. In the
community today that do יבום, yibum, do they force יבום yibum on
an unwilling woman?
I don't, that's a good question, I really don't know the answer
to that.
Second thing, regarding the idea of romantic love, actually really
came
to fruition in the Middle Ages about the time תוספות Tosafos wrote
this, in some of the regions where they were in France and
so forth. So this might have been a little bit of a
reaction to that.
Maybe, maybe. But, you know, look, even in the cases of romantic
love, not every marriage has, you know, is that way, of somebody
being passionately in love. And תוספות Tosafos is still pointing out, not
having an ideal situation is much less worse than having an oppressive,
you know, and having a situation in which you don't have any
options, you don't have any choice, and you're trapped in that type
of a marriage. So תוספות Tosafos very nicely spells out the difference
between why not wanting to marry the guy you hate is a
much more powerful force. Okay, so that's the question. So if it's
a testimony that she doesn't have to do יבום yibum and it
might be, there are definitely cases where
she'll really hate the brother-in-law and there might be real incentives to
not do the due diligence because you really want to get out
of יבום, yibum, and that's a very powerful force. Therefore, maybe we
should not believe the עד אחד eid echad in that case. So
that's the question. אמר להו, Amar lehu, top of צד ד עמוד
א, tzadik daled amud aleph, said to them רב ששת, Rav Sheshet,
תניתוה, tenisua, we learned it in our משנה. mishna. אמרו לה מת
בעליך ואחר כך מת בנך. Amru lah meis ba'alaich ve'achar kach meis
binaiach. They said to her, "Your husband died and then your son
died," so it was in an order in which you're not obligated
in יבום yibum because the husband died and there was still a
living son. וניסת, Veniseis, and then she married some other guy. ואחר
כך אמרו לה חילוף היו הדברים. Ve'achar kach amru lah chiluf hayu
hadevarim. And then they said it was reversed. First the son died
and then the husband, so you were obligated in יבום. yibum. תצא
והולד ראשון ואחרון ממזר. Teitzei vehavalad rishon ve'acharon mamzer. She has to
get divorced and the child is a ממזר. mamzer. Again, why the
child is a ממזר? mamzer? This is רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that
even being עובר over on the איסור issur of a יבמה yevamah
marrying a, you know, a foreign man creates a ממזר. mamzer. But
anyway, the point is that you believe the second testimony over the
first. Why did you believe the second? The second reversed it. Maybe
the first one was right. Why are you giving more weight to
the second testimony? היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אי בשתי
ובשתי? Ei bishtei uveshtei? If the first testimony was two witnesses and
the second was two witnesses, so מאי חזית דסמכת אהני סמוך אהני?
mai chazais desamchas ahanei smoch ahanei? Why do you give, why do
you rely on the second testimony more than the first testimony?
ועוד, Ve'od, and in addition... And it's a ספק, safeik, why is
it ממזר? mamzer? It's why does it say that the child is
a ממזר? mamzer? ספק ממזר הוא. safeik mamzer hu. It's a doubtful
ממזר mamzer because again maybe the first testimony was correct. וכי תימא
לא דק, Ve-chi teima lo dak, maybe it's not being precise? הא
מדקתני סיפא הראשון ממזר והאחרון אינו ממזר, Ha midektani seifa harishon mamzer
ve-ha-acharon eino mamzer, but it says at the end of the משנה
Mishna in a different case that the child before the report was
a ממזר mamzer and the one after is not. You see we
are being very precise. We're being so precise to identify which kid
is a
ממזר. mamzer. So שמע מינה דדווקא קתני, shma mina d'davka katani, we
are being precise. We would not say ממזר mamzer if it was
only a ספק ממזר. safeik mamzer. So clearly you're giving more weight
to the second testimony. Why are you giving more weight to the
second testimony? אלא לאו חד, Ela lav chad, it's all clearly we're
talking about that the first testimony was one witness and the second
testimony was two and therefore the second testimony outweighed the first. הא
טעמא דאתו בי תרי, Ha tama d'atu bei trei, and the reason
that we reversed the first testimony is because afterwards two witnesses came
ואכחשוה ve-achachshueh and they contradicted the one witness. הא לאו הכי, Ha
lav hachi, if it were not for that מהימן meheiman you'd believe.
So the only way to explain in the משנה Mishna why the
second testimony over you know trumps the first is that the first
was עד אחד eid echad and the second was two witnesses. So
if that's the פשט pshat of the משנה Mishna you see that
an עד אחד eid echad testifying that the husband died and then
the kids, which is essentially testifying not only are you free to
remarry because your husband died which we know we believe in עד
אחד, eid echad, but also the order of the death which allowed
her to get out of יבום yibbum that we believe in עד
אחד eid echad even for to allow her to get out of
יבום. yibbum. That sounds like what's going on in the משנה. Mishna.
One sec. So let's see what the answer is. גמרא Gemara says
לעולם תרי ותרי. le-olam trei ve-trei. No, that's not a proof. We
could say the משנה Mishna is talking about two and two. So
why do the second witnesses trump? ורמי רב אחא בר מניומי U-rami
Rav Acha bar Minyumi because this is a case like what רב
אחא בר מניומי Rav Acha bar Minyumi says. בעדי הזמה, Be-eidei hazama,
that the second witnesses are not just contradicting, are not just reporting
opposed facts, but they're actually saying that the first witnesses were not
present at the time that they said that they saw these events.
Okay, that's עדי הזמה. eidei hazama. הכא נמי בעדי הזמה היא, Hacha
nami be-eidei hazama hi, here too it would be that case. So
maybe the reason we overturn it is not because, of course that's
not what the משנה Mishna says. The משנה Mishna says that the
second report says חילוף היו הדברים, chiluf hayu ha-devarim, that the second
report reports the opposite facts. Doesn't say you were with us. Says
it was the reverse of the facts. It's talking about the facts.
But the גמרא Gemara is reading into it that they first of
all you know testified that the first witnesses weren't there, so that
so that made us reject completely the first witnesses and then they
gave the opposite report. Okay, so that's how it's explained the משנה.
Mishna. The משנה Mishna might be talking about two and two and
a particular case where we believe the second witnesses. You can't prove
that the משנה Mishna is talking about only one witness. So therefore
you can't prove that you believe one witness to get this woman
out of יבום. yibbum. There was a question before?
Okay. Before you read that last line, does it just smack of
the logic of עדים זוממים? eidim zomemim? Right, there you go.
Right, but normally we say that explicitly, the משנה Mishna just says
that the second witnesses said the reverse of the first. Okay. Yes.
I mean, wouldn't we also believe in עד אחד eid echad regarding
יבום yibbum right now? Like
if you know if the guy says guess what, you know, dear
wifey you never knew this but I have a brother
brother somewhere? Right. Then עד אחד eid echad says what do you
mean I grew up with this guy and I've never seen him
have a brother? Right.
Well first of all you can't exactly testify to the absence of
something but then there's also questions about right all these cases are
cases where אתחזק itchazek where there's a חזקה chazaka we know what
the facts were beforehand and therefore the עד eid has to work
against those facts. When that's less the case so then there's more
believability and that's something that we'll see later. It's something we pursue
those and so on. Here cases where the facts were well established.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues following. Okay, so it says
like this. אמר ליה רב מרדכי לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Mordechai
le-Rav Ashi, said רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai to רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
ואמרי לה רב אחא לרב אשי, ve-amrei lah Rav Acha le-Rav Ashi,
some said רב אחא Rav Acha said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
so we still don't have an answer to our question. Can you
believe an עד אחד eid echad that she's to get her out
of יבום? yibbum? תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here. האשה שנאמנת
לומר מת יבמי שאנשא. Ha-isha she-ne-emenet lomar met yibami she-innasei.
So we just had before a woman is believed to say my
husband died and the same way an עד אחד eid echad is
believed to say my husband died, a woman's believed to say my
husband died that she can now go ahead remarry or do יבום.
yibbum. What she's not believed to do is to say מת יבמי
שאנשא, met yibami she-innasei, my brother-in-law died so this is exactly the
parallel by the by the woman that we're asking by the עד.
eid. Even her husband's alive or only once he's dead?
No no no, once he's dead. Okay.
מת יבמי שאנשא Met yibami she-innasei that I can marry some other
guy. ולא, Ve-lo, and she's also not believed to say מתה אחותי,
meta achoti,
my sister who my husband, not my husband, who this man was
married to, my sister was married to this man, my sister died
שאכנס לביתו she-ekaneis le-veito now I can marry her husband. Okay, that's
a little bit differently, right? You get it that her sister, right?
לאה Leah is married to יעקב, Yaakov, רחל Rachel is not believed
to say רחל Rachel is not married to יעקב, Yaakov, she's not
believed to say לאה Leah died and now I can marry יעקב.
Yaakov. Okay. Right. Anyway, so anyway a woman is not believed in
these cases which are not about the husband dying and that solves
the problem of אשת איש, eishet ish, but they're about some other
issue about getting out of יבום yibbum or about getting out of
the איסור issur of of two... of two sisters married to the
same man, that a woman is not believed about. Okay, now it's
not exactly clear why this is different. I mean, by the case
of the brother-in-law, it's like we might, it's like we said before,
it might have to do with the fact that she hates the
brother-in-law and therefore she's got a, she could be incentivized to lie.
Why in the case of the sister, she's not believed is less
clear. But anyway, a woman who is believed about her husband's death
is not believed about her brother-in-law's death. So presumably the parallel would
be true about an עד אחד. eid echad. An עד אחד eid
echad would be believed about the husband's death, but not about the
brother-in-law's. Okay, and especially if you assume that the testimony of an
עד אחד eid echad is bolstered by the investigation that the woman
does, so in cases where the woman's own believability is potentially compromised,
we won't believe the עד אחד eid echad either because that's bolstered
by what the woman might be, by the investigation the woman might
be doing. So that seems to be a pretty good prima facie
evidence. So let's take a look. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara first, however, tries to bring it as a
proof to the opposite direction, and let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. היא ניהי דלא מהימנא. hee neehee d'lo meheimna. Maybe she's the
one who's not believed about the brother-in-law dying, הא עד אחד מהימן,
ha eid echad meheiman, maybe the implication is only she isn't believed,
but the normal rule that you believe an עד אחד, eid echad,
maybe that still holds. So that's what he wants to read from
that, that it's only she that is not believed. The גמרא Gemara
says one minute. ולטעמך, u'l'ta'amacha, according to your reasoning, אימא סיפא, eima
seifa, look at the end of that
משנה. Mishnah. אין האיש נאמן לומר מת אחי שייבם את אשתו, ein
ha'ish ne'eman lomar meish achi she'yavem es ishto, a brother is not
believed to say that my brother, let's say he was on a,
he was in a foreign country, died, and now I'm going to
do ייבום yibbum with his wife, ולא מתה אשתי שאשא את אחותה,
ve'lo meisa ishti she'essa es achosa, or not that my wife died
and now I can marry her sister. So a husband isn't believed
in the same cases that the woman isn't believed, the man isn't
believed in these scenarios. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says should we make
the same inference? Should we say הוא ניהו דלא מהימן, hu neehu
d'lo meheiman, that only he is not believed, הא עד אחד מהימן,
ha eid echad meheiman, you would believe an עד אחד? eid echad?
Is that really true? Would you believe an עד אחד eid echad
that a woman's husband is dead and let the brother do, well
let's take a look. הא עד אחד מהימן. ha eid echad meheiman.
בשלמא לגבי אשה משום עיגונא אקילו בה רבנן. bishlama legabei isha mishum
igguna akeilu bah rabbanan. I understand when it's a question about letting
a woman remarry and saying her husband is dead or letting her
say that the brother-in-law is dead and therefore she's free and she
doesn't have to wait for חליצה, chalitza, I understand why we would
believe an עד אחד eid echad in those cases. אלא לגבי איש,
ela legabei ish, but to testify that this man is now let's
say entitled to do ייבום yibbum or more than that he's entitled
to marry this woman's sister, so מאי איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar?
Why is there a special need to believe an עד אחד eid
echad in that case? Okay, so meaning there's a special need to
believe an עד אחד eid echad if the woman's fate is at
stake and otherwise she's trapped. What's a case that she's trapped? Her
husband, we don't know if her husband's alive or dead and he's
overseas, or we don't know if he has to get ייבום yibbum
or חליצה chalitza or not if the brother-in-law's alive or dead, she's
trapped. Those are cases we would believe an עד אחד. eid echad.
Where we wouldn't would be cases where she isn't trapped. Now תוספות
Tosafot actually points out there's a case about the woman where she
isn't trapped, believing the עד אחד eid echad that her sister has
died so let her get married to this guy. She's not trapped,
marry some other guy. Okay, or but by the man also, if
the עד אחד eid echad is saying this woman's husband died, your
brother, you could do ייבום, yibbum, actually we would believe because that
affects the woman and the woman being trapped. But to say
that your wife died so you can marry her sister, he's not
trapped, so we would not believe an עד אחד eid echad in
cases
where the husband is never really trapped. Worst case about the husband
is there's a particular woman he can't marry, but he's never sort
of trapped in a relationship. So therefore,
I mean this is before רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, right? You can
marry multiple wives and so on. A man is never trapped in
a relationship, even if his wife may or may not be alive,
he can always marry another woman. So we would never believe an
עד אחד eid echad for the man. We would only believe it
for the woman and only then in scenarios where she would be
trapped. So when this משנה Mishnah says you don't believe the woman
in these cases and you don't believe the man in these cases,
it is not a valid inference to say you believe an עד
אחד eid echad because there are clearly scenarios here where you would
not believe an עד אחד eid echad because nobody is trapped and
there'd be no basis for believing an עד אחד. eid echad. So
that is not the right read of this משנה. Mishnah. So therefore,
what is the point of this משנה? Mishnah? So therefore the point
of this משנה Mishnah is the following.
אלא כי אצטריך לרבי עקיבא אצטריך. ela ki itztarech l'Rabbi Akiva itztarech.
The משנה Mishnah is telling you not to say you believe an
עד אחד. eid echad. You don't believe an עד אחד. eid echad.
But it's telling you according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva you don't
believe the woman either. What does that mean? סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka
da'atach amina, I would have thought to say, הוא דאמר רבי עקיבא
יש ממזר מחייבי לאוין, hu d'amar Rabbi Akiva yeish mamzer mechayvei lavin,
that since רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said that even from an איסור
לאו issur lav there could be a ממזר, mamzer, אימא חייסא על
קלקולא דזרעא ודייקא, eima chaysa al kilkula d'zar'ah u'dayka,
I might say that if he is saying I don't need to
do ייבום yibbum and I can marry some other guy, according to
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, if she's lying, right, then the child from
her with this other
guy... Maybe I would say she would never lie if the consequence
of the kid would be a ממזר. mamzer. And maybe therefore in
that case I would believe her, קמשמע לן kamashma lan that we
don't believe her. But I'll say in a minute, but at the
end of the day, what the משנה Mishnah should not be read
to infer that you believe an עד אחד eid echad in these
cases. The משנה Mishnah is saying you don't believe her, you don't
believe the man, maybe you don't believe the עד אחד eid echad
either. You should not read it to infer that you do believe
an עד אחד. eid echad. It's just saying you don't believe the
husband and the wife. Now why don't you believe the husband and
the wife? Now we've got a case where
she is saying that according to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, if she's
lying the kid'll be a ממזר. mamzer. And רש"י Rashi also points
out, there's a whole question about whether to include those words in
the parentheses, I won't read them but I'll tell you that רש"י
Rashi points out that not only that, if she's lying also, this
is the question, if a woman marries while awaiting יבום, yibum, and
there's a testimony that the brother-in-law is dead, and she goes and
marries another man and it turns out the brother-in-law's alive, you heap
on her all of the negative consequences that we've been dealing, צא
מזה ומזה ואין לה ולד, Tzei mizeh u-mizeh ve-ein la valad, etc.
So that's based on some earlier סוגיות sugyas and משניות mishnais in
גיטין, Gittin, and רש"י Rashi basically says yes, you do heap all
those consequences on her. So look at this. Right now if she's
lying, the kid'll be a ממזר, mamzer, she'll get all of these
negative consequences, just like our first משנה. Mishnah. Why don't you believe
her in that case? And the answer is that's exactly what we're
asking because maybe she so much hates the brother-in-law that she'd be
willing to lie. So much, because again, it's one thing maybe she's
an עגונה agunah and her husband is overseas,
you understand the incentive to lie, but סך הכל sach hakol right
now she's not living with a man that she hates. The worst
scenario תוספות Tosafot points out would be to have to do יבום
yibum with a man that you really hate. And that is something
that might so incentivize her to lie that we can't believe her
even in a case where were she lying it would have all
of the negative consequences.
Maybe she hates the husband too?
Get him out of that. But the husband is overseas,
so that's important to appreciate that. Nobody is minimizing the issue of
עגונה, agunah, but what the גמרא Gemara is saying is of all
the scenarios, one is your husband is overseas and you don't know
if he's coming back so you can't marry another man. That scenario
one, you can't marry another man. Scenario number two is that maybe
you love your brother-in-law and maybe you'll be lying because you דווקא
dafka want to marry the man you
love. So those are bad situations, particularly the one where she cannot
marry another man. But the worst situation is you'll be forced to
marry a man that you hate. That is the worst of those
three and therefore that maybe is the one that she can't be
believed about and that's what the גמרא's Gemara question is. Seth, you
look skeptical about that.
Seth: It's a very pessimistic view of relationships.
What, that there are cases where you hate somebody? There are cases.
Seth: I know but
that
should be the default?
Why should we be particularly concerned about that case? Let's see how
the גמרא Gemara concludes.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, עד אחד נאמן ביבמה, eid echad neeman b'yevama,
an עד אחד eid echad can be believed even if you don't
believe her, which is important, you can believe the עד אחד eid
echad that the brother-in-law's dead. Why? מקל וחומר. mi-kal vachomer. If איסור
כרת הותר, issur kares hutar, איסור לאו לא כל
שכן? issur lav lo kol shekein? רבא Rava just cut through all
of this question about hate and this and that. He says look,
if you believe an עד אחד eid echad that says she doesn't
have to worry about being married, that the husband is dead and
she doesn't have to worry about the adultery issue, or תוספות Tosafot
also points out and allows her to marry, do יבום yibum with
a brother-in-law, which is also an איסור כרת, issur kares, and you
believe an עד אחד eid echad for all of that, how could
you not believe an עד אחד eid echad to say she doesn't
have to do יבום yibum and she can marry some other man?
The גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה הוא מרבנן לרבא, amar lei hu
meirabanan l'Rava,
but one of the rabbis said to רבא, Rava, no, היא עצמה
תוכיח. hi atzmah tochiach. Look at her herself. דאיסור כרת הותרה, d'issur
kares hutra,
that she is believed to deal with the איסור כרת issur kares
to allow her to say that her husband is dead and she
can marry another man, and she can also believe her to say
that she can do יבום yibum with the brother-in-law which is another
איסור כרת. issur kares. So you believe her about her husband's death,
but לאיסור לאו לא הותרה, l'issur lav lo hutra, you will not
believe her to say the brother-in-law's dead. So you see it's not
just about how weighty it is. We know by she herself you
don't believe her about the brother-in-law. דאלא אי מאי טעמא לא מהימנא,
de-ela i mai tama lo mehamna, so why is she not believed
in the case of the brother-in-law? Like we've been saying, דכיון דזמנין
דסניא ליה, de-kivan de-zimnin de-sanya lei, because there are cases where she
really hates the brother-in-law and she's going to be trapped in that
marriage. לא דייקא ומינסבא, lo daika u-menseva, she's not going to do
due diligence. Maybe she won't consciously lie, but she'll maybe accept insufficient
evidence. Oh, it's pretty good evidence, that's good enough for me to
say that he's dead and she won't do her due diligence. So
that's why you don't believe her even though it's just an איסור
לאו. issur lav. So if that's true, עד אחד נמי, eid echad
nami, דכיון דזמנין דסניא ליה. de-kivan de-zimnin de-sanya lei. לא דייקא ומינסבא.
lo daika uminsava. So if the testimony of an עד אחד ed
echad is backed up by her own research, so if we can't
believe her when she herself testifies, we can't believe the עד אחד
ed echad because she might not do the due diligence in the
case where it's to get her out of marrying the brother-in-law. So
this is really a very gets to the core of the question,
why do we believe the עד אחד? ed echad? Is it totally
based on the testimony of the עד, ed, or is it also
based on the fact that she is doing her own investigation? And
the נפקא מינה nafka mina is a case where we wouldn't trust
her. We won't trust her in the case of the brother-in-law because
maybe she's not going to do due diligence, even if she won't
consciously lie, but she'll accept insufficient evidence because she wants she really
doesn't want to get trapped in that marriage. And if it's a
case where we don't believe her, like about the brother-in-law, will we
believe the עד אחד ed echad or not? And the גמרא Gemara
does not really conclude whether we do or don't. And again, it
really hinges on how much the testimony of the עד ed is
dependent on her own believability. Yes.
What a clarifying question. Neither you nor the גמרא Gemara is using
the language of עדות edut לגבי legabei the woman. Is there a
legal difference between the report of a woman and her status as
עד ed and as being עדות? edut?
Well, not in other cases like for the issue of עד אחד
נאמן באיסורין ed echad neeman bissurin we talk about the עדות edut
of a woman. Here the problem is more that she's a בעל
דין. baal din. You never talk about somebody, man or woman, being
an עד ed for themselves. Okay, so that's really why we're not
using it here. But when a woman comes and testifies that this
woman's husband has died, we do speak about it as עדות אשה.
edut isha. Yes. Right, okay.
And the other question is this line, בשלמא גבי אשה משום עגונה
הקילו רבנן bishlama gabei isha mishum igguna hakeilu rabanan has general inclination
to want to be lenient and flexible in the case of a
potential עגונה, aggunah, has that been mitigated by the following שקלא וטריא
shakla vetarya or does that remain an underlying fundamental principle?
No, it's a it's a total fundamental principle. The question is, you
know, about the issue about
I mean, you are right that in the case where there's a
brother-in-law and we don't know if he's alive or dead, she's also
an עגונה aggunah because she's not free to remarry. Right, so the
גמרא Gemara acknowledges that there's an עגונה aggunah in that case as
well. But again, it doesn't necessarily mean that we can that this
principle will always trump,
allow us to do tremendous קולות kulot in terms of saying that
her husband is dead. But for whatever reason, the גמרא Gemara by
the brother-in-law case felt that, you know, it had to pull back
on that a little bit.
Where do we פוסק? pasken?
Yeah, I don't know. Go ahead, yeah.
Is is רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva opinion about the ממזר mamzer and
the לאו, lav, is that the הלכה? halacha?
No, that I can answer absolutely not. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like
this we don't even answer the question, we just rejected the proof
that you can prove.
Yeah.
I mean, I haven't double checked, but just looking quickly at the
little letter here, I mean I can go ahead and check if
you want on my phone because everything is on my phone.
Hold on, this app, this app ובלכתך בדרך uvelikhtecha vaderech is amazing.
I gotta tell you. I have okay, so let's take a look.
שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, אבן העזר, Even Haezer, קנח, kuf nun chet,
סעיף ג. seif gimel. נאמן עד אחד להעיד ליבמה שמת בעלה ומתייבמת
על פיו, neeman ed echad lehahid leyevama shemet baalah umityabemet al piv,
that we know. או שמת יבמה שתנשא לשוק. o shemet yevamah shetinasei
lashuk. Okay,
so there it is. So we פוסק pasken לקולא lekula like רבא.
Rava. That you do believe, you know, that you do believe at
least the עד אחד. ed echad. You don't believe you don't believe
the woman, but you do believe the עד אחד. ed echad.
Precisely, so maybe it's כדי ש. kidayo shek.
Because right, which is right, which is important again because again, which
by the way gets back to the issue about how much do
we think that all the negative consequences are to create incentive for
her to investigate and how much do we think that the believability
of the עד ed is really because of the investigation that she
is doing, right? And that gets back to some core questions we've
been asking from the beginning of the פרק. perek. Let's let's get
to the משנה. mishnah.
If you don't mind us, why doesn't the סוגיא sugya end with
a תיקו? teiku?
What's the technical it never ends with a תיקו, teiku, it's two
two opinions or two arguments. תיקו teiku is when is when תיקו
teiku is often when you have not really brought any any textual
evidence. You just raise a hypothetical question and say would you say
it this way? Would you say it that way? I don't know.
Moving on. Who knows. תיקו, teiku, right? But almost all debates don't
get resolved in the גמרא. Gemara. I mean, even the הלכתא hilchosas
as we've said, a lot of them are from the גאונים. Geonim.
But תיקו teiku is often when there's like no text to be
brought to get deeper understanding about it. Okay. זה מדרש שאמר אלעזר
בן מתיא. zeh midrash she-amar Elazar ben Mattia. Now the last case
of the משנה mishnah ended that if it turned out that the
that after קידושין kiddushin the husband showed up alive. If there was
testimony the husband was dead and she did קידושין, kiddushin, not נישואין,
nissuin, with another man and then the husband showed up alive. Since
she has not yet started living with the other man, she just
goes back to her husband and it's like no harm, no foul.
Not only that, she doesn't even need a גט get from the
man she did קידושין kiddushin with, she just leaves that and goes
back to her husband. She's never started living with him. And the
משנה mishnah said that if the man that she is the second
guy that she did קידושין kiddushin with gives her a גט, get,
the גט... get... גט get. *get* does not affect her status and
she's not considered a גרושה *Grushah* and she could marry a כהן
*Kohen*, you know, or if the husband is a כהן *Kohen* or
whatever, it doesn't affect her status and he made a דרשה *drasha*
on the פסוק *pasuk* ואישה גרושה מאישה *ve-ishah grushah me-ishah* only if
she's divorced from her husband. And this guy, even though there was
קידושין kiddushin *Kiddushin* is in no way seen as her husband, and
therefore it's not a problem. So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, said רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* in the name
of רב *Rav*, הוי ליה לרבי אלעזר למידרש ביה מרגניתא ודרש ביה
חספא *havay lei le-Rabbi Elazar le-midrash bei marganita ve-darash bei chaspa*. Rabbi
Elazar could have, you know, expounded a pearl from that verse, and
instead he gave a דרשה *drasha* that was like a piece of
pottery. All right, that was a boring דרשה *drasha* that if she's
divorced from a guy, if she gets a גט get, *get* that
isn't her husband, it's not a meaningful גט get *get*. Like that's
pretty obvious. He could have made a much more brilliant interpretation of
the verse. By the way, if you remember just the other day
we said that oh who was it? Somebody said to רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* he says you know הוי ליה לרבי אלעזר למידרש ביה
מרגניתא ודרש ביה חספא *havay lei le-Rabbi Elazar le-midrash bei marganita ve-darash
bei chaspa*, right. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said to רבי ינאי *Rabbi
Yannai*, he said, look, I got this משנה Mishna. *Mishna* that says
what you're saying and he said yeah, but if I hadn't taken
the piece of pottery away, you wouldn't have seen the pearl underneath.
So here you get the same pearl and the pottery. And he
says like this, דתניא De-tanya, *de-tanya*, here's how we could have made
a real good דרשה *drasha* from the פסוק *pasuk*. ואישה גרושה מאישה
*ve-ishah grushah me-ishah*, a woman divorced from her husband, a כהן *Kohen*
cannot marry. אפילו לא נתגרשה אלא מאישה *afilu lo nitgarsha ela me-ishah*,
even if she's only divorced from her husband. What does that mean?
And not permitted to anyone else. What would be the case? The
husband gives her a גט get *get* and says הרי את מגורשת
ממני ואי את מותרת לכל אדם *harei at megureshet mimeni ve-ee at
muteret le-chol adam*. You're divorced from me, but you remain forbidden to
everyone else. So the point is, that type of a גט get
*get*, even though she's only divorced from her husband and not yet
permitted to anyone else, פסולה לכהונה *psula le-khuna*, she's still invalid to
a כהן *Kohen*. והיינו ריח הגט הפוסל בכהונה *ve-hainu reiach ha-get ha-posel
bi-khuna*.
This is the smell of a גט get *get* that's invalid by
כהונה *khuna*. Now that basically is a rabbinic concept, but the point
is is that it's enough has the qualities, the characteristics of a
גט get *get* that even though it's really not valid דאורייתא *d'oraisa*,
it's enough that it has the semblance of a גט get, *get*,
that's the word we would use, that makes her at least invalid
to a כהן *Kohen*. So that's a nice דרשה *drasha*, it's not
you know again unless he's claiming it's a דאורייתא *d'oraisa*, it's an
אסמכתא *asmachta* דרשה *drasha*, but okay, it's a much bigger חידוש *chiddush*
than the way it was used in the משנה Mishna *Mishna*.
And so if he gives her or tries to give such a
גט get *get*, it doesn't work so then they're still married.
So of course she's not allowed to marry.
Well and then he dies. No and then he dies. Okay, the
guy who gives that bad גט get. *get* is a כהן *Kohen*.
Right.
He has to give her a real גט get, *get*. Yeah yeah
that's true. Okay, מי שהלכה אשתו למדינת הים l'medinas hayam. *mi she-halcha
ishto le-medinat ha-yam*. Next משנה Mishna *Mishna*. A man whose wife went
to the faraway country. Instead of the husband going to a faraway
country, she goes on a trip. באו ואמרו לו *bau ve-amru lo*,
they came and said to him, מתה אשתך *meta ishtekha*, your wife
died, ונשא אחותה ve'nasa achosa, *ve-nasa achotah*. So of course he could
anyway even if his wife is alive marry pretty much any woman
in the world except for his wife's sister. Okay, by the way,
that's the only relative that becomes permissible, because all the other relatives
remain forbidden even after the other person has died, right, except for
like if your father's wife. Even after your father has died, she
remains forbidden. The only woman that becomes permissible after somebody dies is
a wife's sister. Because it says ואישה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור
לגלות ערותה עליה בחייה *ve-ishah el achotah lo tikach litzror legalot ervatah
aleha bechayeha*. Okay, so he says the wife has died. Great, now
I'm gonna marry the sister. ואחר כך באה אשתו *ve-achar kakh ba'ah
ishto*, and then his wife shows up. So it's the reverse of
the first case. Okay, so here מותרת לחזור לו *muteret lachazor lo*,
his wife can go back to him. We don't say that somehow
sleeping with his wife's sister makes his wife forbidden to him. Okay,
by the way, it's even funny how it's framed, right? It doesn't
say he's מותר *muttar* to stay married to her, right, it's always
she's מותרת *muteret* to go back to him. It's always the question
about what is her status going to be. Okay and now it
gets to him. ומותר בקרובות שנייה *u-mutar bi-krovot shniyah*, his marriage to
the sister is considered completely meaningless, right, so he doesn't have to
give the sister a גט get *get* for example.
No, she just walks away. And he can marry the relatives of
the sister, right, because it's never like he was married to the
sister. והשנייה מותרת בקרוביו *ve-ha-shniyah muteret bi-krovav*, and the sister can marry
his relatives. It's like that marriage never existed. So as opposed to
the case where the woman marries another man where it's like the
marriage existed and you need a גט get. *get* and they're אסור
asur *assur* in relatives and you have all these negative consequences, here
it's no negative consequences and it's not like he was ever even
married to her. Okay and she walks away without a גט get
*get* and all those things. Right.
So okay, so whatever sin he did, like does he have to
bring a קרבן *korban* or not, whether it was based on הוראת
בית דין *hora'at Beis Din* maybe, but in terms of like other,
you know but other than the question of his sin and guilt,
you know, and maybe not because he did it based on testimony.
Okay, so this woman is now not considered a זונה *zonah*?
Correct. Okay, now why is it different, I mean there's two issues.
Why it doesn't affect her status, the wife's status, should be obvious,
like you know we only have an idea that if a woman...
Or commit adultery or if something happens to the woman's own status
that that can affect her status. Why because something happened with her
sister should that affect her status? So that's the most obvious. But
why is it that we don't look at it as though they
were married and he has to give her גט get and all
those other things? So we'll see more about this in the גמרא,
Gemara, but if you remember one of the reasons the גמרא Gemara
said we look at it like the woman was married to the
other man is because it's possible that the husband was alive and
she was married to the other man. It's possible she was... the
husband gave her a גט. get. So when people see that she
married guy number two and then goes back to guy number one
without a גט, get? right,
they'll say what do you mean? She was married to guy number
two. Who cares if the husband was alive? Maybe she had a
גט get. from the husband. So the fact that the husband was
alive doesn't make it absurd that she could have been married to
guy number two. So the marriage to guy number two is seen
as being meaningful and has its consequences that have to be dealt
with. Whereas in this case if it turns out that the wife
was alive, everybody understands that even if he had divorced his wife
there's no way he could be married to the sister. So therefore
the marriage to the sister is never seen as having any root
in any consequence and therefore doesn't need a גט get. and doesn't
have any of the implications that we've been dealing with.
Okay now, ומתה ראשונה, u'meisa rishona, now let's say his wife actually
does wind up dying, מותר בשנייה, mutar bishniya, there's nothing that prevents
him now from going back to her sister. Okay. אמרו לו, Amru
lo, מתה אשתו, meisa ishto, they said to a man that his
wife had died. ונשא אחותה, he married the sister. ואחר כך אמרו
לו, ve'achar kach amru lo, קיימת הייתה ומתה, kayyemes hayesa u'meisa, and
then they said to her, actually when we first told you she
had died and you married the sister she actually was still alive,
now she's dead. Okay so in that case, הולד ראשון ממזר, havlad
rishon mamzer, the child that he had with the sister when it
turns out his wife was still alive is a ממזר, mamzer, because
that's clearly a child that results from an איסור עריות. issur arayos.
והאחרון אינו ממזר, ve'ha'acharon eino mamzer, the child that he has after
the wife has really died would not be a ממזר. mamzer. רבי
יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, Rabbi Yosi says, כל שפוסל על ידי
אחרים פוסל על ידי עצמו, kol she'posel al yedei acherim posel al
yedei atzmo, anybody that invalidates through others invalidates through themselves. וכל שאין
פוסל על ידי אחרים אינו פוסל על ידי עצמו, ve'chol she'ein posel
al yedei acherim eino posel al yedei atzmo, and if you don't
invalidate through others you don't invalidate through yourself. Well that's clear enough.
Alright so I don't have to say anything... anyway that's not clear
at all what he's saying. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara how
the גמרא Gemara interprets what that means. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואף
על גב דאזיל אשתו וגיסו למדינת הים. ve'af al gav de'azil ishto
ve'giso l'medinas hayam. So when it says
you don't that that excuse me that
you don't
right that there's no lasting consequences to the fact that he married
the sister that would be even in the following scenario: His brother-in-law
and his wife went on a trip. Okay so meaning okay ראובן
Reuven is married to שמעון Shimon right? I'm sorry ראובן Reuven is
not married to שמעון, Shimon, thank you. Okay ראובן Reuven is married
to רחל Rochel alright, not שמעון, Shimon, somebody else. ברוך Baruch is
married to לאה, Leah, alright? Got it? Okay should we get back
to that? Yes. Oh my god it's been so long since we
did that. Okay here we go.
So גיסו giso means brother-in-law? Yes.
That was the
whole time you were away. I know.
Okay here's somebody else, here's ברוך. Baruch. Okay so ראובן Reuven is
married to רחל Rochel and ברוך Baruch is married to לאה. Leah.
Now who goes on a trip? The people that go on a
trip are this probably dead by now gotta put caps on רחל,
Rochel, his wife, and his brother-in-law they go למדינת הים. l'medinas hayam
Okay they go to some trip. Now which means and then the
report is both of these have died. Since both of these have
died his wife has died, that means that he could marry לאה,
Leah, and ברוך Baruch and לאה's Leah husband is died now he
can marry לאה. Leah. Got it? So if only one of them
had died he'd be stuck right? Because either לאה Leah is still
married or or she's still his living sister you know he's married
to the sister. But if both of these guys if רחל Rochel
and ברוך Baruch his wife and his brother-in-law have gone למדינת הים
l'medinas hayam and the report is they're both dead now he's free
to marry לאה. Leah. Okay so that's what happens.
What? That's the point.
Okay right. So right. So okay so ואף על גב דאזיל אשתו
וגיסו, ve'af al gav de'azil ishto ve'giso, his wife and brother-in-law have
gone למדינת הים and the witnesses come back and say and a
witness comes back and says what he says דהני הני נישואין דקא
מיצרכא אשת גיסו אגיסו. de'hani hani nisuin deka mitzrecha eshes giso a'giso.
So what happened? He goes ahead and he now marries לאה. Leah.
Then we find out that the report that then ברוך Baruch and
רחל Rochel come back, they were alive. Okay what's going to be
the consequence for לאה? Leah? From לאה's Leah perspective what has happened?
A witness has come and said her husband is dead right? ברוך
Baruch is dead. And she went ahead and she married ראובן. Reuven.
Now it turns out that the husband is alive. So what what?
So here לאה Leah gets all the negative consequences right? All the
negative stuff okay? Okay that's what happens to לאה Leah all of
the negative consequences when it turns out they're alive so maybe if
לאה Leah gets all those negative consequences heaped on her because the
Testimony turned out to be false, maybe some of that should also
extend somehow to רחל. Rachel. That if she's being invalidated by the,
by that bad testimony, maybe somehow רחל Rachel would be invalidated as
well. And the point is not. Okay, but the גמרא's Gemara just
spelling that out. דהני הני נשואין, Dehani hani nisuin, the first marriage
to, to, you know, that לאה Leah now, the marriage that לאה
Leah had with ראובן Reuven was strong enough that it heaps on
לאה Leah all of these negative consequences when it turns out it's
false.
דהני הני נשואין דקמצרא אשת גיסו אגיסו, Dehani hani nisuin dekamtzra eshet
giso agiso, his brother-in-law's wife לאה Leah is now forbidden to his
brother-in-law. אפילו הכי Afilu hachi and therefore you might say look, if
because they were married and לאה's Leah going to suffer all those
consequences, you know, because it looks like a marriage here, so if
it looks like a marriage maybe vis-à-vis רחל Rachel it also looks
like a marriage and it looks like he was married to לאה.
Leah. And if he was married to לאה, Leah, he can't go
back and be married to רחל. Rachel. Right, you understand the logic
of it, right? If we're saying it looked like they were married
and therefore she's in this terrible situation now, well heck, if it
looked like they're married, then how can he go back and live
with the sister if he had looked like he was married to
לאה? Leah? So nevertheless,
אפילו הכי אשת גיסו אסירה אשתו שריא, Afilu hachi eshet giso asira
ishto sharya, his brother-in-law's wife is forbidden to his brother-in-law, his wife
remains permissible to him. ולא אמרינן רחל ומתוך שנסרה אשת גיסו אגיסו
תיאסר אשתו עליו,
Velo amrinan Rachel
umitoch shenesra eshet giso agiso te'aser ishto alav, and we don't say
רחל Rachel and because לאה Leah is now forbidden to his brother-in-law,
that רחל Rachel should now be forbidden to him. And somehow we
say no, that basically, and it is a little ironic because again,
what is the reason why we don't say it looks like he
was married to her? We don't say it looks like he was
married to her for the reason I said that once it turns
out that לאה Leah was alive, there's no scenario that he could
have been married to רחל Rachel and also been married to לאה.
Leah. So therefore we don't look at it like they were married.
But if we don't look at it like they're married, she shouldn't
have to suffer the consequences with ברק. Barak. But we say she
does. We say in this way we apply the standard situation, the
standard idea that the husband was testified as dead, it looked like
she was married to another man, all the negative consequences. But in
this case says yeah, but you know what his marriage to another
woman does not affect his existing marriage to his wife. Now, one
of the ways of understanding that is of course the idea that
in general, you know, it is the woman whose status is affected
by marriage, the woman's status is affected by forbidden sexual acts, you
know, I mean the man is forbidden to do sexual acts but
it's never his status that's affected. The woman becomes a חללה chalala
when she has certain types of forbidden sexual acts, right, the woman
becomes אסור asur to her husband when she has certain types of
forbidden sexual acts. It's the woman becomes totally forbidden to everybody else
when she gets married. So it's the woman's status that can get
affected. But here since he was sleeping with לאה, Leah, right, it's
not going to affect his wife's status because she's not the one
that was involved in anything and that's I think part of the
logic here as well.
And what happens to לאה Leah in this situation?
In this situation, she has to be divorced from both husbands, תצא
מזה ומזה, tetzei mizeh umizeh, the whole first משנה.
Mishna She gets two גטין. gettin.
Exactly. Okay, so that's where the גמרא Gemara points out the irony
here. Okay,
so רמי מתניתין דלא כרבי עקיבא. Rami matnitin dela k'Rabbi Akiva. Now
let's say our משנה is not like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דאי
רבי עקיבא, De'i Rabbi Akiva, it's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva הויא ליה
אחות גרושתו hava lei achot grushato
because according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, he's saying she would have
to give a גט get,
to לאה. Leah. Forget now the whole ברק Barak point. We're going
to ignore the ברק Barak point a minute. Okay, so he had
been married to לאה, Leah, she thought he was married to לאה,
Leah, turns out that לאה Leah was alive. Okay, turns out that
רחל Rachel was alive, excuse me. Now according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, he does have to give a גט get to לאה. Leah.
And if he does have to give a גט get, to לאה
Leah because they were seemingly married, then רחל Rachel becomes his divorcee's
sister because לאה Leah looks like his divorcee. Right, once you say
that this marriage looks like it existed, the whole reason the משנה
didn't have consequences, that לאה Leah didn't need a גט, get, that
רחל's Rachel status wasn't changed, was because we said it was never
looked, it never looked like a marriage. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
it does look enough like a marriage. He does.
וצריכה גט מזה ומזה.
Utzricha get mizeh umizeh. Exactly.
That was when there was a husband, that confused you. Yes, but
ignore ברק. Barak. That was just because we applied the normal status,
but in a case where forget ברק, Barak, there's just a wife
and a sister. Okay, the fact that he's married to a sister
when it turns out רחל Rachel was alive in hindsight never looks
like it was a marriage because we know that רחל Rachel was
alive the whole time. And therefore the משנה says that she doesn't
need a גט get. and she's free from consequences and she's free
from consequence also. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, even in
this case לאה Leah needs a גט. get If it turns out
right because it looked like they were married for a time. Once
לאה Leah needs a גט, get רחל Rachel is going to be
אסור because then we're saying that it looks like this was a
marriage. If it looks like this was a marriage and she becomes
his divorcee, then the sister becomes forbidden.
Even though he was married to רחל Rachel first anyway?
Yes. Okay, it's a type of a תצא מזה ומזה. tetzei mizeh
umizeh. It's living with the consequences of what happens once it looked
like a marriage. And then you have to draw all the natural
consequences. דאי רבי עקיבא, De'i Rabbi Akiva, if it's רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva הויא ליה אחות גרושתו. hava lei achot grushato. רחל Rachel now
becomes the sister of the woman he divorced. Now where do we
see רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says he
has to give רחל, Rachel, where, רחל? Rachel?
Where do we see רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says he has to
give a גט get. to לאה? Leah? I'm just testing you to
see if you're paying attention. דתניא, we return a ברייתא: braita: כל
אלו שבתורה kol elu she-ba-Torah אין צריכה ממנו גט. en tzericha mimenu
get. If anybody did any איסור עריות issur arayas in the Torah
and they started living with their sister or their father's wife or
whatever it was, no need even if they did קידושין kiddushin, and
נישואין nisuin it's completely meaningless, no need for a גט. get, חוץ
מאשת איש שנישאת על פי בית דין. Chutz me-eshet ish sheniset al
pi beit din. The only time that we need a גט get.
is a woman married another man because there was testimony that her
husband was died. That case we said looks like a real marriage
and because maybe the husband divorced her who knows just even if
it turned out the husband was alive, in that case when the
husband shows up she needs a גט get, and it has all
the consequences. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, ורבי עקיבא מוסיף אף
אשת אח ואחות אשה. ve-Rabbi Akiva mosif af eshet ach ve-achot isha.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva adds even a
you know the wife of your brother's wife or your sister's sister
or your wife's sister. Now what is the logic for those two?
So the logic for those two is, I would say number one
is, these are cases where you're not they're not blood relatives, right?
Somebody's living with his you know his sister, right, or his aunt
or whatever it is, right, so it's obvious to everybody this isn't
a marriage. Like that's incest, it's blood relatives, it's obvious there isn't
a marriage. Okay, but there are other cases which are not blood
relatives which רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would not demand a גט. get
A man married his father's wife. It's not a blood relative, his
father is dead, why wouldn't that require a גט? get. So the
other important point besides not being blood relatives is that in both
of these cases that there are scenarios where they become alive father's
wife or become permissible father's wife will never be permissible. But how
can brother's wife be permissible? יבום, Yibum, if the brother died. יבום.
Yibum. How can wife's sister be permissible? If the wife died. So
these are the two עריות arayot that are neither blood relatives and
are both not blood relatives and are scenarios where they might be
permissible. So these are cases where רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says if
it you went ahead and married them, you know based on whatever
reason, either you intentionally violated or based on testimony, whatever reason turns
out you were married to this person and it wasn't legitimate, it
looks enough like a marriage that you still have to give these
women גט. Okay, so that's a reasonable position. So if רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva going to say that it looked like while רחל Rachel
was in מדינת הים, Medinat Ha-yam, this looked enough like a real
marriage, people would say oh he can't really be married to לאה
Leah it's his wife's no they think maybe she's dead. So since
this looked enough like a real marriage at least in the time
even if in hindsight it doesn't, לאה Leah needs a גט. And
once לאה Leah needs a גט, right, רחל Rachel must now be
forbidden to him. Okay, you got that?
It's not only it looks like a marriage experientially, formally from a
legal perspective it could be.
It's but right it could be, right, I mean it wasn't but
it could have been. Right. Okay, so וכיון דאמר ve-kivan de-amar רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, since רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says by a גט
that לאה's Leah going to need a גט, so ממילא איתסרא ליה,
mi-mela it'sera leh, so then as a natural result רחל Rachel will
become forbidden to him. דהוי ליה אחות גרושתו. de-hava leh achot gerushato.
Okay, so that seems like a reasonable point. גמרא Gemara says one
minute, we're going to pull back on רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't we're going to say he didn't really mean
that. אלא איתמר עלה Ella itmar alah one minute, it was said
to explain רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
חייא בר יוסף אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Chiya bar
Yosef amar Rav, האי אשת אח היכי דמי? hai eshet ach hechi
dami?
When רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that brother's wife needs a גט,
what's the scenario?
כגון שקידש אחיו את האשה, ke-gon she-kiddesh achiv et ha-isha, that the
brother was only married to this woman only קידושין, kiddushin not נישואין.
nisuin. והלך למדינת הים ושמע שמת אחיו, ve-halach li-medinat ha-yam ve-shama she-met
achiv, and then his brother went on a trip and you heard
that he was dead, ועמד ונשא אשת אחיו, ve-amad ve-nasa eshet achiv,
and then he married the wife. דאמרי אינשי de-amri inshi because then
the reason it looks like a קידושין kiddushin, like it looks like
he was married to his brother's wife even though his brother had
already done קידושין, kiddushin is because people will say maybe that קידושין
kiddushin really never took, because people will say the קידושין kiddushin. that
the brother did, הך קמא hach kama the first husband תנאי הוה
ליה בקידושין, tnai hava leh be-kiddushin, maybe there was some stipulation in
the קידושין. kiddushin. ושפיר נסב ve-shappir nasa and therefore the brother you
know the guy who the second guy really married well and therefore
you need a real גט. So what he's saying is רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva never meant that if it turned out that the woman
was originally you know fully married there was נישואין nisuin to you
know in these cases that the second guy would need a גט
because that doesn't look like a marriage. The only case where it
looks like a marriage even in the case of wife sister or
brother's wife is if the first marriage was only קידושין. kiddushin Since
sometimes קידושין kiddushin without נישואין nisuin will fall through if it's on
a תנאי. tnai. Normally we say אין תנאי בנישואין en tnai be-nisuin
once they've started living together stipulations are no longer legitimate to undermine
it. That gets into all suggestions nowadays about working with עגונה agunah
situations and so on. Okay, but we normally say that תנאים tna'im
stipulations that that make it all dependent on certain conditions being met
work at the קידושין kiddushin stage not at the נישואין nisuin stage
as a general rule. So if there was just קידושין kiddushin, with
the first husband then we could say with the second guy you
need a גט because people might think that it fell through. But
after נישואין nisuin you wouldn't need a גט. And similarly...
Exactly, and similarly,
the והא אחות אשה נמי, ve-ha achot isha nami, the case of
wife's sister, היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? כגון דקידש אשה,
kegon dekiddash isha, he married one woman, רחל, Rachel,
קידושין, kiddushin not נישואין, nissuin, והלך למדינת הים, ve-halach limdinat ha-yam, and
רחל Rachel went away, ושמע שמתה, ve-shama she-meta, and he heard that
רחל Rachel died, עמד ונשא אחותה, amad ve-nasa achota, then he married
לאה. Leah. דאמרי אינשי, de-amri inshi, people will say, yeah, he was
really married to לאה. Leah. Why? Because the marriage to רחל Rachel
never went through. הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha be-mai askinan, תנאי הוה ליה
בקידושין, tenai hava lei be-kiddushin, the first woman רחל, Rachel, there was
a stipulation, והא שפיר נסיב, ve-ha shapir nasiv, and that, and the
wedding to לאה Leah really was good. Okay, אלא נישואין מי איכא
למימר, ela nissuin mi ika lemeimar, but if there was really a
נישואין nissuin in the first marriage, who, how could anybody say תנאי
הוה ליה בנישואין, tenai hava lei be-nissuin, that there was a תנאי?
tenai? So therefore, even though it sounds like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
would say that sometimes we see other cases as a real marriage
and really requiring a גט, and that's a bad thing because then
you have to deal with all the negative consequences, the גמרא Gemara
severely limits רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and says that those were only
in cases where the first relationship was a קידושין one, so it
was not real and therefore maybe it would be perceived as never
really having taken. But if the first relationship was a נישואין nissuin
one, you will never need a גט. And since you won't need
a גט, לאה Leah will never need a גט if he has
really had נישואין nissuin to רחל, Rachel, and therefore, even when it
turns out that רחל, Rachel, when it turns out רחל Rachel is
alive, ראובן Reuven is free to go back to רחל. Rachel. לאה
Leah doesn't need a גט. Everybody is much better off if we
wind up in hindsight seeing it as it actually was, as not
having been a real marriage. Okay, so we'll end with this for
now. And I do not know what is wrong with my...